Preliminary Guide to the Clements Collard Fry Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Clements Collard Fry papers
1771-1969
1920-1955
MS 1290
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.29
(6 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, financial material, book orders, memorabilia, writings, and printed matter of Clements Collard Fry. Also included is a collection of S. Weir Mitchell material, 1771-1929, including writings, notebooks, photographs, correspondence, announcements, appointments, clippings, and printed matter.
Fry, Clements Collard, 1892-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980 and 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born in 1892, Clements Collard Fry received a bachelor of science degree from Michigan State University in 1917. In 1923, he received an M.D. degree from Northwestern University and three years later, began working at Yale University. In 1930, he became the head of the department of mental hygiene at Yale, a position he held until his death on November 24, 1955. Fry was a collector of documents related to the history of medicine and especially Silas Weir Mitchell. Silas Weir Mitchell (1829-1914), who was a doctor, acclaimed writer, and prominent member of Philadelphia society. He died on January 4, 1914.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, financial material, book orders, memorabilia, writings, and printed matter of Clements Collard Fry. Also included is a collection of S. Weir Mitchell material, 1771-1929, including writings, notebooks, photographs, correspondence, announcements, appointments, clippings, and printed matter.
Medicine; Fry, Clements Collard, 1892-1955; Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914
- Inventory
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [bibliographies of material in or not in Fry collection], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir correspondence, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, et al. "Report of a Committee of the Associate Medical Members of the Sanitary Commission on the Subject of Scurvy with Special Reference to Practice in the Army and Navy", 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clements C. Fry correspondence, 1938, 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mitchell, John K. "The Digestive Functions." Lecture., n.y. April 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [bibliography of material in Fry collection], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "S.W.M. Chronology", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "Collected Reprints, Vol. 1, 1858-1882", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [articles about], 1914-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [reprints of articles by], 1864, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [auction catalogue of Mitchell library], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [articles, addresses, exhibits relating to], 1902-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles in publications such as Harper's Weekly, The Century, and Atlantic Monthly, sometimes relating to/written by S.W. Mitchell, 1866-1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Timothy Pickering to L. Baldwin, Boston, 1827 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: L. Baldwin to Timothy Pickering, 1827 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drawing of Timothy Pickering, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: "[B.S. Stuart?] to William B. Tyler, Baltimore [with envelope], 1868 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Isabel Frances Dodd to S.W. Mitchell, 1908 January [28?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: M.D. Post to S.W. Mitchell, 1918 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "Ode on a Lycian Tomb" [typed manuscript], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles and poems, 1814-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [articles by], 1909, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cataloged cards not included in Burr bibliography, 1969 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "A Copy of a Case of Lunacy sent by Prince Henry to S. John Doddridge", undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "A Magnolia Bud in the Garden of the Armenian [Convent?] at Venice," "Labor," and "Translations", 1840-1846 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, [review of S. W. Mitchell's three books on rattlesnake venom], 1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "Remarks on the Effects of Anhelonium Lewinii (the Mescal Button)," The British Medical Journal, pp. 1625-1628., 1896 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Plates, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - University of Pennsylvania Proceedings of Commencement, 1903 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous scraps, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - L'Indienne [used as scrapbook of medical clippings], Circa 1771-Circa 1808 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, [medical/scientific notebook, with illustrations], Paris, 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [notebook], 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, Count of the Wine [wine book], Circa 1899 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [notebook-writings], undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [biography], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [material relating to Franklin Inn Club], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Tubes of Galli," Paris, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Regulations for the Medical Department of the C.S. Army", 1862 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "A Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year to the Sons of the University of Pennsylvania" [calendar], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Hospital Register, Orange [Court House?], VA. Battle of [Wilderness?]-May 4th 1864-Surg B.S. Herndon in charge" (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [photograph], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "Little Mother" [poem], 1896 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "The Christ of the Snow, A Norwegian Legend," [Christmas card], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [printed document relating to the Maryland Club], 1894 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, "Ave Pennsylvania" [poem], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Channing, Walter, "Some Remarks on the Address Delivered to the American Medico-Psychological Association, By S. Weir Mitchell, M.D., May 16, 1894", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Button with letter "I", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Mitchell, Silas Weir?] [notebook-poems/writings], At Sea, Ship Badeu-Badeu, 1888 August (Box 1, Folder 23a)
  - General correspondence [some to C.C. Fry], 1935-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fry, Clements C. [Correspondence]
    - G, 1930-1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Ha-Hi, 1930-1950 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Harper & Brothers Publishers, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Ho-Hu, 1931-1950 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Hollander, H.S., 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Holman's print shop, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 29A)
    - Hoosier Bookshop, 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - [Relating to hypnosis], 1930 May-June (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - [Relating to hypnosis: "no experience in and no opinion about Hypnosis"], 1930 May-October (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - [Relating to hypnosis: respondents do consider there to be after-effects], 1930 May-June (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - [Relating to hypnosis: respondents consider there to be after-effects only under certain circumstances], 1930 May-June (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - [Relating to hypnosis: respondents consider there to be no harmful after-effects], 1930 May-June (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Fry, Clements C. [notes and correspondence relating to after-effects of hypnosis], 1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Writings
    - [Relating to insanity], undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - [Typed manuscript, possibly part of a history of psychiatry], undated (Box 2, Folder 38 - 39)
    - "Journeys in Delirium" [typed manuscript], undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Fry, Clements C., "Mental Hygiene and Freshman Counseling" [reprint from Mental Hygiene 23:2 (Apr 1939): 268-276; originally a talk to freshman counselors at Yale University] (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Fry, Clements C., "Psychotherapy" [with bibliographies], undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Retrospect and Prospect: A Special Report on the Twenty-Fifth Anniversary of the Student Mental Hygiene Service at Yale", 1951 June (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Sex", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "Some Origins in Psychiatry" [lecture notes and possibly related correspondence], Circa 1935 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "The College Student" and "Administrative Problems in College Health....A Summary", 1954 January 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Psychiatry - general lecture - notes, writings, publications
    - Rademacher, E.S., "Psychosis of Dejection," Mental Hygiene News 10:4 (Apr 1931). (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Yale Daily News, 1936 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Campbell, C. Macfie, "Commensense [sic] and Insanity" [lecture], undated (Box 2)
  - Papers and articles [mostly by others], 1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - National Research Council, Division of Medical Sciences, Committee on Psychiatry: Minutes of the Fourth Meeting [Fry a member], 1952 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - [Reports and panel discussions for Yale University], 1948-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Barker, Lewellys F., "The Relations of Endocrinology to Psychiatry" [lecture and related correspondence], 1927 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Lecture IX", undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - [Lectures, lecture notes, and articles without author or not by Fry], undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures and articles without author or not by Fry], 1929-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "Unconscious" [notes and paper], undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "Current Cases July 1, 1929" [students with description of problem] (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - [Lecture and lecture notes], undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - [Unidentified typed manuscript relating to personalities], undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - "Bestor", undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - [Publications], 1926-1952 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - [Directories], 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - "A Tenth Catalogue of Rare Books & Manuscripts" [catalogue of items for sale], undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - "The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease Books Received" [heavily annotated bibliography relating to psychology], undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - [Miscellaneous notes], undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - [Notes, clippings, and correspondence], Circa 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - [Typed notes on various articles], undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - "Outline of Research Project to Evaluate the Adjustment of Known Neurotic Individuals in the Armed Services" [including other notes for research], undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - [Notes on doctors], undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - [Scrapbook of clippings and drawings], Circa 1653-Circa 1832 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - [Medical journal with pasted clippings], Circa 1850 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - [Scrapbook/medical journal], Circa 1790-1860 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - [Thomas, Theodore G.], "Diseases of Women" [notes on], 1878 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - "V.W. Northrop. Castleton VT", 1840 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [scrapbook containing correspondence and poems by Mitchell and others], Circa 1852-Circa 1909 (Box 4)
  - [Scrapbook of charts, articles, and examinations relating to child psychology], Circa 1926 (Box 5)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, Hugh Wynne: press notices [scrapbook], Circa 1897-1898 (Box 5)
    General
    Box 6 no longer exists. Its contents have been rehoused in box 5.
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [scrapbook of correspondence, invitations, grades, admission tickets to medical courses, clippings, awards, and other documents], 1847-1911, undated (Box 7)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir [contract to become medical officer in Union army], 1863 May 25 (Box 7)